Guide to the Undergraduate Faculty Council Records, 1952 - 1972 UA.28.01.0003
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Undergraduate Faculty Council records
1952 - 1972
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. Undergraduate Faculty Council
UA.28.01.0003
6 Linear Feet
Formed in 1952, the Undergraduate Faculty Council (UFC) was responsible for the governance of undergraduate education at Duke University. The Undergraduate Faculty Council of Arts and Sciences succeeded the UFC in October 1971, when undergraduate education in engineering and nursing formed separate governing bodies. Collection includes minutes, memoranda, correspondence, questionnaires, reports of standing and ad hoc committees, and other papers pertaining to faculty oversight of undergraduate education. The bulk of the material consists of the records of the Subcommittee on Curriculum, a part of the Committee on Undergraduate Instruction. Other committees include Honors, Program II, the Faculty Advisory System, Residential Life, Study Abroad, Undergraduate Admissions, Financial Aid, and Academic Standards. One of the major accomplishments of the UFC was a report called "Varieties of Learning Experience," or the Krueger Report (1968), which led to major changes in the undergraduate course of study known as the "new curriculum." English.
4200 Items
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist.
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Undergraduate Faculty Council Records was received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1964-1992.
Historical Note
Undergraduate Faculty Council began in 1952, as a result of a re-organization of the Duke University Faculty. The Undergraduate Faculty Council (UFC) was responsible for the governance of undergraduate education, a task that the Faculty Council previously had undertaken. The UFC included representatives from the Engineering and Nursing schools. The Dean of Trinity College served as chair. The UFC first met on November 13, 1952. The Undergraduate Faculty Council of Arts and Sciences succeeded the UFC in October 1971, when undergraduate education in engineering and nursing formed separate governing bodies.
Standing Committees of the Undergraduate Faculty Council included Undergraduate Instruction (which absorbed the Curriculum Committee and the Committee on Courses of Instruction between 1964-1965), Honors, Program II, the Faculty Advisory System, Residential Life, Study Abroad, Undergraduate Admissions, and Financial Aid. Ad hoc committees included Academic Standards, Committee on Committees, and the Committee on the Organization and Functions of the UFC. The creation of a report called "Varieties of Learning Experience," or the Krueger Report (1968), represents one of the major accomplishments of the Undergraduate Faculty Council. The Krueger Report led to major changes in the undergraduate course of study known as the "new curriculum."
Collection Overview
Collection includes minutes, memoranda, correspondence, and questionnaires, reports of standing and ad hoc committees, and other papers pertaining to faculty oversight of undergraduate education. The bulk of the material consists of the records of the Subcommittee on Curriculum, a part of the Committee on Undergraduate Instruction. The Subcommittee's records feature the Krueger report, "Varieties of Learning Experience (1968), which led to the substantial changes in the undergraduate courses of study known as the "new curriculum." These files include results of a survey of faculty members and freshmen participating in small group learning experiences. The other major curriculum study is the Parker report (1960).
The Program II files contain material from the period after 1971, when the Undergraduate Faculty Council of Arts and Sciences was formed. Records of the Supervisory Committee for the Faculty Advisory System include scattered minutes of the committee, memoranda, correspondence, and reports, as well as handbooks for faculty advisers from 1952 to 1964. A number of ad hoc and superseded committees' files are also in the collection.
Related Material
Undergraduate Faculty Council of Arts and Sciences records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Education, Higher -- Curricula; Education, Higher -- Aims and objectives; Duke University. Undergraduate Faculty Council of Arts and Sciences; Duke University. Program II; Duke University -- Students; Duke University -- Faculty; Duke University. Undergraduate Faculty Council; Duke University. Undergraduate Faculty Council; Duke University -- Administration; Duke University -- Admission; Duke University -- Curricula; Duke University -- Faculty -- Handbooks, manuals, etc.
- Executive Committee, 1952-1971
  Scope and Contents note
  The Executive Committee series contains agendas, correspondence, minutes, petitions, rosters, and lists of the standing committees of the Executive Committee of the Undergraduate Faculty Council. Topics include the reorganization of the faculty, committee appointments, and petitions to suspend classes for the 1961 Cotton Bowl.
  - Agendas, 1954-1971 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1952-1961 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1962-1970 (Box 1)
  - Minutes, 1952-1960 (Box 1)
  - Minutes, 1961-1962 (Box 1)
  - Minutes, 1963-1964 (Box 1)
  - Minutes, 1965-1967 (Box 1)
  - Minutes, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Minutes, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Minutes, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Minutes, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Petitions, 1958, 1960 (Box 1)
  - Rosters, 1959-1971 (Box 1)
- Committees, 1953-1971
  - Advisory Committee on Committees, 1962-1970
    This series contains correspondence of the Advisory Committee on Committees of the Undergraduate Faculty Council. Topics include bylaws, student participation, and committee appointments.
    - Correspondence, 1962-1970 (Box 1)
  - Committee on Academic Standards, 1953-1968
    - Correspondence, 1956-1964 (Box 1)
    - Minutes, 1963-1964 (Box 1)
    - Reports, 1954-1968 (Box 1)
    - Attrition studies (Box 6)
    - Committee files, 1954-1962 (Box 6)
    - Correspondence, 1953-1956 (Box 6)
    - Minutes, 1953-1955 (Box 6)
    - Minutes, 1955-1956 (Box 6)
    - Reports, 1955-1958 (Box 6)
    - Minutes, 1956-1962 (Box 7)
  - Committee on Courses of Instruction, 1948-1971
    This series includes agendas, correspondence, course approvals, minutes, and proceedings of minutes of the Committee on Courses of Instruction of the Undergraduate Faculty Council. Topics include the approval of proposals for new courses, programs, and professors.
    - Agendas, 1965-1971 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1951-1954 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1955 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1956-1957 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1958 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1959 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1960 (Box 1)
    - Course Approvals, 1970-1971 (Box 1)
    - Minutes, 1948-1964 (Box 1)
    - Minutes, 1965-1969 (Box 1)
    - Proceedings of Minutes, 1948-1960 (Box 1)
    - Proceedings of Minutes, 1961-1965 (Box 1)
  - Committee on the Organization of the Undergraduate Faculty Council, 1962-1971
    This series contains correspondence, minutes, and reports of the Committee on the Organization of the Undergraduate Faculty Council. Documents include a detailed report on the organization and the functions of the Undergraduate Faculty Council.
    - Correspondence, 1965-1966 (Box 1)
    - Minutes, 1963 (Box 1)
    - Reports, 1962-1964, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Committee on Study Abroad, 1961-1971
    This series contains correspondence between educators at Duke and other institutions such as Vanderbilt and Stanford, minutes, program brochures, reports, and student records of the Committee on the Study Abroad of the Undergraduate Faculty Council. This series also contains one photograph, which is housed in a folder labeled "miscellaneous." Topics include program designs, descriptions of summer study programs, academic qualification of students, and recommendations.
    - Correspondence, 1961-1967 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1968-1969 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1970-1971 (Box 2)
    - Minutes, 1961-1971 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous, 1962-1971 (Box 2)
    - Programs, 1966-1971 (Box 2)
    - Reports, 1962-1976 (Box 2)
  - Committee on Undergraduate Instruction, 1953-1967
    This series contains correspondence, newspaper clipping, notes, proposals, publications, and reports of the Committee on Undergraduate Instruction of the Undergraduate Faculty Council. Topics include curriculum proposals, committee appointments, and education program reviews. Publications include the Academic Guide for Freshman, the Manual of Style for Duke Undergraduate Term Papers, and the Duke University Faculty Newsletter.
    - Correspondence, 1964-1966 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 1967 (Box 2)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1967 (Box 2)
    - Notes, 1966-1967 (Box 2)
    - Proposals, 1963-1967 (Box 2)
    - Publications guide, 1964-1965 (Box 2)
    - Publications, 1953-1964 (Box 2)
    - Publications, 1965-1967 (Box 2)
    - Reports, 1964 (Box 2)
    - Reports, 1965-1967 (Box 2)
    - Subcommittee on Curriculum, 1958-1971
      This series contains correspondence, minutes, newspaper clippings, notes, publications, questionnaires, and reports of the Subcommittee of the Curriculum of the Committee on Undergraduate Instruction of the Undergraduate Faculty Council. This series includes multiple drafts of the Krueger Report, called "Varieties of Learning Experience" (1968), which is a curriculum study funded by the Board of Education of the Methodist Church. Topics include committee appointments, work-study, honors program, the arts, physical education, and other curricular matters from faculty, alumni, and student groups.
      - Correspondence, 1965-1966 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence, 1967 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence, 1968 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence, 1968 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence, 1969-1971 (Box 2)
      - Krueger Report -- Drafts, 1967-1968 (Box 2)
      - Krueger Report, 1968 (Box 2)
      - Krueger Report -- Papers, 1968 (Box 2)
      - Minutes, 1965-1969 (Box 2)
      - Newspaper Clippings, 1966-1968 (Box 2)
      - Notes, 1967-1971 (Box 3)
      - Publications, 1958; 1964-1967 (Box 3)
      - Questionnaires, 1960, 1968 (Box 3)
      - Questionnaires, 1970-1971 (Box 3)
      - Reports, 1965-1966 (Box 3)
      - Reports, 1967 (Box 3)
      - Reports, 1967 (Box 3)
      - Reports, 1968 (Box 3)
      - Reports, 1968 (Box 3)
      - Reports, 1968-1969 (Box 3)
      - Reports, 1969-1971 (Box 3)
      - Reports--PER, 1967-1968 (Box 3)
      - A.G. Reichenberger (Box 3)
      - Current Meeting, 1971 (Box 3)
      - 1971 (Box 3)
      - Personal documents, 1971 (Box 3)
      - Comparative Literature, 1970 (Box 3)
      - Grading, 1969-1970 (Box 3)
      - Graduating with distinction in interdisciplinary programs (Box 3)
      - Humanities, comparative literature, 1970 (Box 3)
      - Duke University Research Council, 1971 (Box 3)
      - Minutes, 1970-1971 (Box 3)
      - Interdisciplinary Programs, 1970 (Box 3)
      - Miscellaneous corresondence (Box 3)
      - New Curriculum, 1968 (Box 3)
      - Report, 1971 (Box 3)
      - Questionnaire (Box 3)
      - Questionnaire, 1970 (Box 3)
      - Questionnaire results, 1970 (Box 3)
      - Questionnaire, comments (Box 3)
      - Nursing, 1969 (Box 3)
      - Materials from Ballantyne, 1968-1970 (Box 3)
      - Paramedical program, 1970 (Box 3)
      - Physical Education Requirement, 1969-1970 (Box 3)
      - Physical Education Major, 1967-1970 (Box 4)
      - Physical Education, 1971 (Box 4)
      - Report, 1971 (Box 4)
      - Report, 1971 (Box 4)
      - Unfinished business, 1969-1970 (Box 4)
      - Wilson House, 1970 (Box 4)
      - Zoology, Beaufort Program, 1970 (Box 4)
      - Medieval and Reinaissance Studies (Box 4)
      - Bruce Wardropper, memoranda and correspondence, 1970-1972 (Box 4)
      - Minutes, proposals and reports (Box 4)
      - Foreign Language Requirements (Box 4)
      - Memoranda, correspondence, minutes and reports (Box 4)
      - Unclassified (Box 4)
    - Subcommittee on Grading, 1965-1970
      This series contains correspondence, newspaper clippings, and reports of the Subcommittee on Grading of the Committee on Undergraduate Instruction of the Undergraduate Faculty Council. Topics include modification of the grading system, the possible institution of a plus and minus grading system, the pass-fail grading system, and academic standards and grading.
      - Correspondence, 1966-1970 (Box 4)
      - Newspaper Clippings, 1965-1966 (Box 4)
      - Reports, 1965-1966 (Box 4)
    - Subcommittee on Policy, 1964-1971
      This series contains memoranda, reports, and minutes of the Subcommittee on Policy of the Committee on Undergraduate Instruction of the Undergraduate Faculty Council. Topics include administering the plus and minus grading system, the pass-fail grading system, the structure of the subcommittee, and subcommittee appointments.
      - Memoranda and Reports, 1968-1971 (Box 4)
      - Minutes, 1964-1968 (Box 4)
      - 1971 (Box 4)
  - Curriculum Committee, 1955-1969
    This series contains agendas, correspondence, and reports of the Curriculum Committee of the Undergraduate Faculty Council. Topics include curricula reviews, course approval requests, course revisions, long-range planning, and curriculum models for undergraduate education.
    - Agendas, 1958 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, 1955-1959 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, 1960 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, 1961 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, 1962-1964 (Box 4)
    - Reports
      - CSRL, 1969 (Box 4)
      - General, 1957-1960 (Box 4)
      - General, 1961-1964 (Box 4)
      - General, 1964-1965 (Box 4)
      - Parker Report, 1959-1960 (Box 4)
      - Parker Report, 1961 (Box 4)
  - Supervisory Committee for the Faculty Advisory System, 1952-1972
    This series contains Faculty Advisors' Handbooks, correspondence, and reports of the Faculty Advisory System of the Undergraduate Faculty Council. Topics include pre-registration, curricula, the pass-fail grading system, advisement schedules, and reports pertaining to the faculty advisory program.
    - Faculty Advisors' Handbook, 1952-1957 (Box 4)
    - Faculty Advisors' Handbook, 1958-1959 and undated (Box 4)
    - Faculty Advisors' Handbook, 1960-1962 (Box 5)
    - Faculty Advisors' Handbook, 1963-1964 (Box 5)
    - SCFAS Correspondence, 1952-1966 (Box 5)
    - SCFAS Reports, 1955-1971 and undated (Box 5)
  - Program II Committee, 1969-1972
    This series contains agendas, correspondence, minutes, reports, and student proposals of the Program II Committee of the Undergraduate Faculty Council. Topics include general program information, committee appointments, student applications with proposals, and graduating with distinction. Program II allowed students to design their own plan of study.
    - Agendas, 1970-1972 (Box 5)
    - Correspondence, 1970-1972 (Box 5)
    - Minutes, 1969-1972 (Box 5)
    - Reports, 1970-1971 (Box 5)
    - Student Proposals, 1971-1971 (Box 5)
    - Student Proposals, 1971-1972 (Box 5)
    - Student Proposals, 1972-1972 (Box 5)
- Robert Charles Krueger Files, circa 1967-1972
  This series contains the files of Robert Charles Krueger, who headed the Curriculum Committee which overhauled the undergraduate curriculum. His reforms allowed students leeway to select more elective courses from a broader range of disciplines.
  Conditions Governing Access note
  *These boxes are unprocessed and may contain restricted information. Consultation with Archives staff may be required prior to use.*
  - Robert Charles Krueger files (Box 8-11)